Guide to the Daily Worker and the Daily World Negatives Collection PHOTOS.223.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Daily Worker and the Daily World Negatives Collection
1930-2001
1968-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Party of the United States of America
Andrews, Bill, 1937-
PHOTOS.223.001
36 Linear Feet
The Daily Worker was established as the Communist Party USA's daily newspaper in 1924. As the official organ of the Communist Party USA (CPUSA), the Daily Worker's editorial positions reflected the policies of the party while also attempting to speak to the broad left-wing community in the United States that included labor, civil rights, and peace activists. The newspaper has had a succession of names and has been published in varying frequencies between daily to weekly over the course of its existence. In 2010 it ceased print publication and became an online weekly publication titled the People's World. The Daily Worker and the Daily World Negatives Collection contains printed photographic images produced through a variety of processes, created and collected by the photography editors of the Daily Worker and its successor newspapers as a means of maintaining an organized collection of images for use in publication. The collection dates from 1930 to 2006, with the bulk of the material dating from 1930 to 1948 and from 1968 to 1990. The images depict people, groups, and events associated with the CPUSA. The collection contains approximately 670,000 photographic negatives in various formats; contact sheets and log sheets related to 35 millimeter negatives; and several hundred slides. NOTE: Access to Series I and Series II is closed through 2025 pending digitization.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the Daily Worker and Daily World Negatives Collection was transferred to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives as part of the donation of the Communist Party of the USA archives and the Library of the Reference Center for Marxist Studies in the summer of 2006. Additions to the collection include several linear feet of material received from Daily World staff photographer and artist Bill Andrews in January 2010. The accession number associated with the Bill Andrews materials is 2011.120.
Scope and Contents
The Daily Worker and the Daily World Negatives Collection contains printed photographic images produced through a variety of processes, created and collected by the photography editors of the Daily Worker and its successor newspapers as a means of maintaining an organized collection of images for use in publication. The collection dates from 1930 to 2006, with the bulk of the material dating from 1930 to 1948 and from 1968 to 1990. The images depict people, groups, and events associated with the Communist Party USA (CPUSA). The collection contains approximately 670,000 photographic negatives in 4" x 5", 8" x 10", and 120, 127, and 35 millimeter formats; contact sheets and log sheets related to the 35 millimeter negatives; and several hundred slides. The negatives were mostly shot by Daily Worker and Daily World staff photographers, with additional negatives sent to the paper by readers and other individuals. Slides were also largely shot by staff photographers, but the collection does contain a few commercially-produced thematic slide sets, mostly from the Soviet Union and Soviet bloc countries. The majority of the negatives are of New York City people and events, despite the international coverage of the newspaper.
Images from the 1930s and 1940s focus heavily on the activities of organized labor and the relationship of the CPUSA to local and national labor unions, particularly those affiliated with the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO). Images include strikes, union meetings and elections, union social events, and parades. Images from 1968 to 1990 focus on CPUSA activities, leaders, members, and affiliated organizations. These include portraits of Gus Hall, Henry Winston, Angela Davis, and Jarvis Tyner, and images of Mark Rudd, Abbie Hoffman, Stokely Carmichael, John Kerry, H. Rap Brown, Paul O'Dwyer, Adam Clayton Powell, Bella Abzug, John Lindsay, Nelson Rockefeller, Percy Sutton, Jacob Javits, Charles Rangel, Vito Marcantonio, Rhody McCoy, and C. Herbert Oliver.. There are also negatives of conventions, demonstrations, and meetings of the CPUSA, Young Workers Liberation League, Young Communist League, and W. E. B. Du Bois Clubs. The civil rights and anti-Vietnam War movements are documented through images of the Black Panther's Breakfast Program in Harlem, New York City police raiding Louis Farrakhan's Muslim Mosque, Moratorium Day demonstrations, and other anti-war demonstrations. The arts and sports are also documented in the collection, including St. Patrick's Day parades, the New York City Marathon, Apollo mission astronauts at City Hall, Aretha Franklin in concert at the Apollo Theater, jazz musicians at the Village Vanguard, and a 1968 W. E. B. Du Bois centennial meeting at Carnegie Hall whose participants included Martin Luther King, Jr. and James Baldwin. Also included are images of celebrity supporters of liberal or left-wing political causes, mainly actors such as Paul Newman, Lauren Bacall, Dustin Hoffman, Ed Asner, Ossie Davis, and Ruby Dee. Images of city life include ice cream trucks, New Jersey's Palisades Park amusement park, public school openings, and the Brooklyn-Long Island Cat Show. Images related to professional sports and athletes include sports teams affiliated with labor unions, the Hermann Matern Sports School in the German Democratic Republic, exhibition games between United States (US) and Soviet Union teams, Jim Bouton, Joe Frazier, and Muhammad Ali. Images of people and events outside of the US in the collection focus on Cuba, Chile, and the Soviet Union. From Cuba, there are images of Che Guevara, Fidel Castro, the percussion ensemble Los Papines, and events including the 1970 Organization of Latin American Journalists conference and the 1978 World Festival of Youth and Students in Havana, Cuba. From Chile, there are images of rural cooperative farms, and a 1971 May Day parade in Santiago whose participants include Salvador Allende. There are numerous images of people and events in the Soviet Union, many taken on CPUSA delegations. A large percentage of these depict CPUSA leaders including Gus Hall and Henry Winston, images of rural life in Tajikistan and the Kirghiz Soviet Socialist Republic, and international conferences, including the 1985 World Festival of Youth and Students, a 1988 United States-Soviet Union Friendship Summit in Moscow, and the 1963 World Congress of Women in Moscow.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Daily Worker/Daily World Photographs Collection (PHOTOS 223)
Communist Party of the United States of America Audio Collection (TAM 132.1)
Communist Party of the United States of America Oral Histories (OH 065)
Communist Party of the United States of America Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 031)
Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM 132)
Although the Daily Worker and Daily World Photographs Collection and the Daily Worker and Daily World Negatives Collection have the same provenance, the original order of each collection was very different from the other. Negatives were arranged by shoot, while prints were arranged by personal name or subject. As a result, finding a corresponding negative for a given print (or vice versa) is not always easy or even possible.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series:
Series I: 4 x 5, 120 and 127 Negatives, Series II: 35 Millimeter Negatives, Series III: 8 x 10 Negatives, Series IV: Slides, Series V: Log Sheets, Series VI: Contact Sheets
Series IV negatives are arranged alphabetically by shoot caption and Series V materials are arranged in chronological order. Dated negatives in Series I through III and in Series VI are arranged chronologically, followed by undated negatives arranged alphabetically by caption. In addition, all the negatives series in the collection may also be viewed in one combined list arranged in alphabetical order by caption, by clicking on the following link: http://library.nyu.edu/tamiment/dw_negs_sorted_by_shoot_title.pdf
Captions are assigned to a shoot, which is a group of images shot by a photographer or team of photographers of one event, usually on the same day. Each shoot has a unique identifying number. The 4x5, 120, 127, and 8x10 format negatives have been assigned individual frame numbers within each shoot as well (making it possible for researchers to determine in advance the total number of images available in a given shoot). 35 millimeter negative shoots (and any corresponding log or contact sheets for them) do not have assigned individual frame numbers, but the total number of frames within each 35 millimeter shoot ranges from one single frame to several rolls comprising as many as 100 individual images, with an average of 36 frames images per shoot.
While the shoot numbers for the 35 millimeter negatives, contact sheets, and log sheets correspond to one another, none of these groups of materials completely match one another. That is, not all 35 millimeter negatives have corresponding contact sheets or log sheets and vice versa.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to Series I and Series II is restricted until June 2025 pending digitization. Once digitization is complete, digitized access copies will be available online and access to the physical materials will be restricted.
Materials in Series III through Series VI are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
The Daily Worker was established as the Communist Party USA's daily newspaper in 1924. The newspaper was initially established as the weekly The Worker in 1921 when the Communist Labor Party (CLP) merged with the Workers Party in 1921 and the CLP's newspaper, The Toiler, became the The Worker. The newspaper was published in Chicago, Illinois until 1927, when the headquarters of the Communist Party USA (CPUSA) moved to New York, New York. As the official organ of the CPUSA, editorial positions of the Daily Worker reflected the policies of the party while also attempting to speak to the broad left-wing community in the United States (US) that included labor, civil rights, and peace activists. The newspaper published stories covering a wide range of events, organizations, and individuals in the US and around the world.
As a daily newspaper, it covered the major stories of the twentieth century with an emphasis on radical social movements, social and economic conditions in working class and minority communities, poverty, labor struggles, racial discrimination, right wing extremism with an emphasis on fascist and Nazi movements, the Soviet Union, and the world-wide Communist movement. The newspaper published the work of many graphic artists and cartoonists, including Fred Ellis, Hugo Gellert, Robert Minor, and Ollie Harrington, and documented the relationship between politics and folk music and folk dance, covering individuals such as Woody Guthrie, Pete Seeger, Leadbelly, Sophie Maslow and Martha Graham. The newspaper reported on the civil rights movement, including sit-ins, voter registration campaigns, and the Freedom Rides and as well as the work of individuals and organizations, including Martin Luther King, Jr, Ralph Abernathy, Rosa Parks, Adam Clayton Powell, Jr., the Black Panthers, the Soledad Brothers, and Angela Davis.
The newspaper has had a succession of names and has been published in varying frequencies between daily to weekly over the course of its existence. In 2010 it ceased print publication and became an online weekly publication titled the People's World.
Separated Materials
Original cartoons and artwork were separated to the Daily Worker/Daily World Cartoons Collection (GRAPHICS 024). Printed ephemera was separated to the Communist Party of the United States of America Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 031).
Sponsorship Information
Detailed processing for this collection was made possible by a grant from the National Historical Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC).
Sources
"Daily Worker." Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia. Wikimedia Foundation, Inc. 30 June 2011. Web. 20 Sep. 2011.
"Daily Worker (and Successors)." Encyclopedia of the American Left. Mari Jo Buhle, Paul Buhle and Dan Georgakas. Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1992.
Gottfried, Erika. "Shooting Back: The Daily Worker Photographs Collection," American Communist History, 12:1, 41-69 (Spring 2013).
Schappes, Morris U. "The Daily Worker: Heir to the Great Tradition." New York: Daily Worker. Jan 1944.
New York (N.Y.) -- History -- 20th century -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century -- Pictorial works.; Labor unions -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Picketing -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Sports -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Strikes and lockouts -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Labor unions and communism -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Anti-war demonstrations -- United States -- Pictorial works.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Civilian relief -- Pictorial works.; Contact sheets.; Negatives (photographic); Slides (photographs); African Americans -- Pictorial works; Communists -- United States -- Portraits.; Demonstrations -- Pictorial works.; May Day (Labor holiday) -- Pictorial works.; Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1862-1951 -- |v Pictorial works; Allende Gossens, Salvador, 1908-1973 -- |v Pictorial works; Amter, I. (Israel), 1881-1954 -- |v Pictorial works; Abzug, Bella S., 1920-1998 -- |v Pictorial works; Ali, Muhammad, 1942- -- |v Pictorial works; Abernathy, Ralph, 1926-1990 -- |v Pictorial works; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926 -- |v Pictorial works; Davis, Ossie -- |v Pictorial works; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961 -- |v Pictorial works; Dellinger, David T., 1915-2004 -- |v Pictorial works; Conyers, John, 1929- -- |v Pictorial works; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965 -- |v Pictorial works; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964 -- |v Pictorial works; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944- -- |v Pictorial works; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016 -- |v Pictorial works; Chisholm, Shirley, 1924-2005 -- |v Pictorial works; Chavez, Cesar, 1927-1993 -- |v Pictorial works; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973 -- |v Pictorial works; Bussi de Allende, Hortensia -- |v Pictorial works; Huerta, Dolores, 1930- -- |v Pictorial works; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978 -- |v Pictorial works; Jackson, Jesse, 1941- -- |v Pictorial works; Hall, Gus -- |v Pictorial works; Harrington, Oliver W. (Oliver Wendell), 1912-1995 -- |v Pictorial works; Ho, Chí Minh, 1890-1969 -- |v Pictorial works; Gerson, Simon W. -- |v Pictorial works; Gorbachev, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1931- -- |v Pictorial works; Gregory, Dick -- |v Pictorial works; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963 -- |v Pictorial works; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961 -- |v Pictorial works; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985 -- |v Pictorial works; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- |v Pictorial works; Johnson, Hewlett, 1874-1966 -- |v Pictorial works; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006. -- |v Pictorial works; Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954 -- |v Pictorial works; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005 -- |v Pictorial works; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet) -- |v Pictorial works; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-2013 -- |v Pictorial works; Kirkpatrick, Frederick Douglass -- |v Pictorial works; Kissinger, Henry, 1923- -- |v Pictorial works; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968 -- |v Pictorial works; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924 -- |v Pictorial works; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969 -- |v Pictorial works; Koch, Ed, 1924-2013 -- |v Pictorial works; International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO) -- |v Pictorial works; Distributive, Processing, and Office Workers of America. District 65 -- |v Pictorial works; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America. District 65 -- |v Pictorial works; Weinstock, Louis, 1903-1994 -- |v Pictorial works; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union. Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union (New York, N.Y.) -- |v Pictorial works; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965 -- |v Pictorial works; Winston, Henry, 1911-1986. -- |v Pictorial works; Communist Party of the United States of America -- |v Pictorial works; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- |v Pictorial works; Mooney, Thomas J., 1882-1942 -- |v Pictorial works; Patterson, William L. (William Lorenzo), 1890-1980 -- |v Pictorial works; North, Joseph -- |v Pictorial works; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976 -- |v Pictorial works; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972 -- |v Pictorial works; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945. -- |v Pictorial works; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979 -- |v Pictorial works; Mitchell, Charlene, 1930- -- |v Pictorial works; Ford, James W., 1893-1957 -- |v Pictorial works; Tyner, Jarvis -- |v Pictorial works; Young Communist League of the U.S. -- |v Pictorial works; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America -- |v Pictorial works; 1199, National Health and Human Service Employees Union -- |v Pictorial works; Young Workers Liberation League -- |v Pictorial works; Andrews, Bill, 1937-; Communist Party of the United States of America
- Series I: 4 x 5, 120 and 127 Negatives
  Scope and Content Note
  Contains just over 1,600 groups of large-format 4x5 inch negatives, as well as medium-format 120 and 127 negatives, dating mostly from 1930 to 1948. Most of these images are of people and events based in New York City, and include a large number of images of labor union strikes, demonstrations and other activities. Of particular significance are photos of May Day celebrations and demonstrations in New York City, activities supporting the Spanish Republican cause, Communist Party of the United States of America candidates for election to local, state, and federal offices, and pictures of daily life in New York City from the early to mid-20th century.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to this series is restricted until June 2025 pending digitization. Once digitization is complete, digitized access copies will be available online and access to physical materials will remain restricted.
  - Tom Mooney and His co-Defendants. From Left to Right, Edward D. Nolan, Tom Mooney, Rena Mooney, Warren Billings and Israel Weinberg., 1917; cuid37018 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00001-01)
  - Sacco and Vanzetti Case - Demonstrations for Defendants. Rose Baron stands 3rd from right, with glasses. Alfred Wagenknecht is at right, in bus entrance., Aug 1927; cuid37019 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00002-01 - 00002-02)
  - Fred Ellis at his desk at the Daily Worker., May 1930; cuid37020 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00003-01)
  - Fred Ellis with Ethel and Bobby in Berlin., 1930-1931; cuid37021 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00004-01)
  - Israel Amter Election Campaign., Fall 1931; cuid37022 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00005-01 - 00005-04)
  - Ford Motor Company Hunger March., 1932; cuid37023 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00005A-01 - 00005A-04)
  - Earl Browder with the Scottsboro Boys., 1931; cuid37024 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00005B-01)
  - Communist Party of the United States of America - Demonstration Against Adolf Hitler (New York, New York)., Apr 1933; cuid37025 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00006-01 - 00006-03)
  - 72nd Street and Riverside Drive, New York City. Photos by Herman "Pat" Herst, Jr., 1933; cuid37026 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00006A-01 - 00006A-03)
  - Centre International de L'enfance, Paris., Sep 1934; cuid37027 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00007-01)
  - Fred Ellis., Oct 9, 1934; cuid37028 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00008-01)
  - Peace Demonstrations., 1934-1941; cuid37029 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00009-01 - 00009-03)
  - Petition-Signing on Lower East Side, New York City., Jun 1935; cuid37030 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00009A-01 - 00009A-11)
  - President Franklin Delano Roosevelt Signing Social Security Bill., Aug 1935; cuid37031 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00010-01)
  - Frank [Fred?] Ellis., Jun 1936; cuid37032 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00011-01)
  - 9th National Convention Communist Party of the United States of America., Jun 28, 1936; cuid37033 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00012-01 - 00012-05)
  - Labor Carnival on Randall's Island, New York., Jul 11, 1937; cuid37034 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00013-01 - 00013-27)
  - Communist Party Mass Demonstration at Japanese Consulate to Protest Japanese Invasion of China., circa 1937; cuid37035 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00013A-01 - 00013A-13)
  - Peter V. Cacchione Kings County Campaign Headquarters. 98 4th Ave, Brooklyn, New York., Sep 21, 1937; cuid37036 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00014-01 - 00014-07)
  - Daily Worker Birthday Party., Jan 13, 1938; cuid37037 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00015-01 - 00015-08)
  - Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy and the American Student Union Fleet of Ambulances. Donated by Students and Friends of Swarthmore College., Mar 17, 1938; cuid37038 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00016-01 - 00016-05)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade., Mar 17, 1938; cuid37039 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00017-01 - 00017-10)
  - International Brotherhood of Painters Contingents in the Union Label Parade., May 16, 1938; cuid37040 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00018-01 - 00018-12)
  - Peace Parade., June 1938; cuid37041 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00019-01 - 00019-08)
  - Making Floats for August 6 Peace Parade., 1938; cuid37042 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00020-01 - 00020-02)
  - International Brotherhood of Painters Election., 1938; cuid37043 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00021-01 - 00021-16)
  - Demonstrations for Spanish Republic, Madison Square Garden (New York, New York)., July 19, 1938; cuid37044 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00022-01 - 00022-16)
  - Second group of Spanish Civil War prisoners arriving from Spain on the SS Washington., Winter 1938; cuid37045 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00023-01 - 00023-05)
  - United May Day Conference. Defeat Tammany., 1938; cuid37046 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00024-01 - 00024-11)
  - Peace Council Strike with Speakers Dr. Harry F. Ward (Chairman), Chao Ting Chi (Editor of Amerasia), Jay Allen ( New York Post Spain Correspondent), A.J. Northwood (NSFA Neutrality), J.W. Wise (American League for Peace and Democracy), William E. Dodd (U.S. ambassador to Germany, 1933 - 1937)., 1938; cuid37047 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00025-01 - 00025-21)
  - Food Supply For Relief Ship For Spain., 1938; cuid37048 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00026-01 - 00026-05)
  - Demonstration For State Housing., 1938; cuid37049 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00027-01)
  - Rehearsal For Madison Square Garden Demonstrations For Spanish Republic., 1938; cuid37050 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00028-01 - 00028-08)
  - [Dr. Reisig?] Going To Spain., 1938; cuid37051 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00029-01 - 00029-03)
  - Joe North in Spain during Spanish Civil War Holding Child., 1938; cuid37052 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00030-01)
  - Rockwell Kent Painting and Drawing Signs and Posters to Raise Fund for the Relief Ship for Republic of Spain in front of Father Duffy Monument (Times Square, New York)., 1938; cuid37053 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00030A-01 - 00030A-11)
  - May Day Parade., May 1, 1939; cuid37054 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00031-01 - 00031-26)
  - Joseph Olgin Moissaye Banquet., Summer 1939; cuid37055 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00032-01 - 00032-04)
  - Madison Square Meeting - Anniversary Celebration of 22 years of the U.S.S.R., Nov 1939; cuid37056 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00033-01 - 00033-06)
  - Joseph Olgin Moissaye Body in State, Vindsor [Windsor?] Palace., Nov 1939; cuid37057 (Box 1a, Shoot-negative 00034-01 - 00034-05)